Guide to the Jerry Oberwager Papers TAM.826
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jerry Oberwager Papers
1930-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Oberwager, Jerry
Amatniek, Kathie
TAM.826
4 linear feet in 6 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 record carton, and 2 oversize folders in shared housing
96 film loops filmstrips
Jerome "Jerry" Oberwager (1917-2017) was a political artist and activist. Oberwager participated in an arts-in-residence program in Mexico in the late 1930s, and later worked as a model maker in the United States Army during World War II. He later worked at the newly formed United Nations, making educational filmstrips for UNESCO. Oberwager had multiple entrepreneurial pursuits to support himself, including reproductions of colonial furniture and biological teaching aids. He co-founded Vagabond Puppeteers in upstate New York. The Jerry Oberwager Papers (dated 1930-2006) consists of materials created and collected by Oberwager documenting his military service, the businesses he ran to support his artistic endeavors, and his engagement with a number of leftist social movements in the mid- and late-20th century. Materials in this collection documenting Oberwager's activities as a politically engaged artist include photographs, correspondence, and ephemera from an arts-as-education program and a UNESCO project in Mexico; ephemera from Oberwager's arts-related businesses; and ephemera, photographic prints, and filmstrips documenting his work in the audiovisual department of the United Nations producing education filmstrips. Many of the filmstrips documented in this collection are teaching aids about the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights. Other materials document leftist social movement groups Oberwager was involved in, with particular emphasis on organizations in the Great Neck area of Long Island. The collection also includes a small amount of ephemera documenting the founding and activities of the Vagabond Puppeteers. The collection also documents Oberwager's military service, and includes official service records, research notes, and photographic prints. Some of the photographs depict graphic wartime injuries and others documenting Oberwager's model-making and puppetry depict racist caricatures.
Scope and Contents
The Jerry Oberwager Papers (dated 1930-2006) consists of materials created and collected by Oberwager documenting his military service, the businesses he ran to support his artistic endeavors, and his engagement with a number of leftist social movements in the mid- and late-20th century. Materials in this collection documenting Oberwager's activities as a politically engaged artist include photographs, correspondence, and ephemera from an arts-as-education program and a UNESCO project in Mexico; ephemera from Oberwager's arts-related businesses; and ephemera, photographic prints, and filmstrips documenting his work in the audiovisual department of the United Nations producing education filmstrips. Many of the filmstrips documented in this collection are teaching aids about the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights. Other materials document leftist social movement groups Oberwager was involved in, with particular emphasis on organizations in the Great Neck area of Long Island. The collection also includes a small amount of ephemera documenting the founding and activities of the Vagabond Puppeteers. The collection also documents Oberwager's military service, and includes official service records, research notes, and photographic prints. Some of the photographs depict graphic wartime injuries and others documenting Oberwager's model-making and puppetry depict racist caricatures.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kathie Amatneik in June 2023; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.075.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Biographical Note
Jerome "Jerry" Oberwager (1917-2017) was a political artist and activist. Oberwager participated in an arts-in-residence program in Mexico in the late 1930s, and later worked as a model maker in the United States Army during World War II. He later worked at the newly formed United Nations, making educational filmstrips for UNESCO. Oberwager had multiple entrepreneurial pursuits to support himself, including reproductions of colonial furniture and biological teaching aids. He co-founded Vagabond Puppeteers in upstate New York.
Appraisal
The following items were appraised out the collection at the point of acquisition: microslide sets, published texts already in Tamiment Library holdings, published texts outside of the Tamiment Library collecting areas, duplicate materials, newspaper clippings without immediate context, source photography, select examples of Oberwager's artwork, and mounted images. There is ample documentation of Oberwager's work creating and distributing microslide viewers; the viewers themselves are outside of Tamiment's collecting scope. The collection includes many examples of Oberwager's craft and artwork; a stained glass window kit, a Darwin poster, an image of a chalkware figuring, and bicentennial artwork were returned to the donor.
Puppet theater.; New Left.; Politics in art.; Social movements in art.; Social movements.; Amatniek, Kathie; United Nations
- Clippings on Chile, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Mexico, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Craft -- Liberty Workshop Chalkware and Jewelry, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Craft -- Research and Resources, 1934-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Craft -- Sculpture and Restoration, 1934-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Educational Pamphlets, Mexico, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Human Rights, 1969-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Left Groups -- Great Neck Marxist Forum, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Left Groups -- Great Neck SANE, 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Left Groups -- Long Island Alliance Upsurge, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Left Groups -- Long Island Coalition for Democracy, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Left Groups -- SOA Watch, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Navaho Sand Art", undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- National Teaching Aids, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Notes and Research, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Oberwager Family Tree, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Pátzcuaro Film Strip Scripts, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Pátzcuaro UNESCO Work, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 6, Box 7, Folder 10)
- Personal Political File, 1953-1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1937-2006 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
- Ray of Light Assistive Device, 1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Schools (Great Neck), 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9, Box 5, Folder 1)
- Subject Files -- Direct Action, 1999-2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Subject Files -- Unions, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- United Nations -- Film Photographic Prints, 1940s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 1-9, Box 6, Folder 11)
- United Nations -- Film Scripts, 1947-1967 (Box 5, Folder 4-7, Box 6, Folder 10)
- United Nations -- Work, 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 8-11)
- US Army -- Model-Making and Puppetry Show (Racist Depictions), 1944 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- US Army -- Service Record and Military Research (Graphic Images), 1944-1946 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
- US Army -- SOP Manual, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
- Vagabond Puppeteers, 1930-2006 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)